Guide to the Alvin Orloff and Michael Collins papers, 1986-2011.
Orloff, Alvin and Michael Collins papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Alvin Orloff and Michael Collins papers, 1986-2011.
7789
Orloff, Alvin,
Approximately 1 cubic feet (427 leaves of manuscripts and 935 items).
Correspondence, photographs, printed material
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Manuscripts, ephemera, photographs, posters, clippings, and other materials documenting the queer punk, performance and club scenes in San Francisco from the mid-1980s through the mid-1990s, at a time when AIDS was devastating the city's gay population and when the activist groups ACT UP and Queer Nation emerged in response to the epidemic. The papers focus on the Popstitutes and the many other initiatives by Collins and other group members and associates in the following decade, including Playstitute and Klubstitute. The personal collection of manuscripts, ephemera, posters, photographs and other materials documenting the groundbreaking queer punk, performance and club scenes in San Francisco from the mid-1980s through the mid-1990s, at a time when AIDS was devastating the city's gay population and when the activist groups ACT UP and Queer Nation emerged in response to the epidemic. With more than 425 leaves of typescripts and manuscripts and more than 900 items of ephemera and related materials, the collection offers rich primary sources for research in cultural studies, gender studies, queer studies, contemporary history, theater history, art history and related disciplines. The papers focus on The Popstitutes - a seminal San Francisco queer performance group and punk band founded in 1986 by Michael Collins ("Diet Popstitute," 1958-1995); Brad Kellogg ("Bad Popstitute"); and Alvin Orloff ("Remix von Popstitute")-and on the dizzying array of activities spawned by Collins and the other members and associates of the group in the decade that followed.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Alvin Orloff played a major role in the Popstitutes, an influential San Francisco queer performance group and punk band founded in 1986 by Michael Collins ("Diet Popstitute"), Brad Kellogg ("Bad Popstitute"), and Orloff ("Remix von Popstitute"). He was also important in Playstitute, a production company that brought genderbending and avant-garde plays and musicals to established theatrical spaces in San Francisco, and Klubstitute, a long-running weekly club that featured underground queer performance in a variety of genres. Orloff also served as an impresario and DJ at Baby Judy's, a queer dance club held weekly in San Francisco's Mission District from 1994 to 1996. Michael Joseph Collins, aka Diet Popstitute, was a performance artist, musician, theater producer, and club entrepreneur. Born in 1958, he died in 1995 at the age of 37. In the late 70s, Diet moved to San Francisco and became known in the Punk Rock scene. He wrote poetry, which later developed into his song lyrics. In 1986, he co-founded the musical and queer performance art group The Popstitutues with Alvin Orloff, aka Remix von Popstitute, and Brad Kellogg, aka Bad Popstitute. Stage shows featured choreographed dances, costumes, and props, and promoted The Popstitutes belief in sexual liberation and self expression. While such shows were message-driven comedy, The Popstitutes musical style was impossible to categorize. In 1990, The Popstitues opened Klubstitute, a floating queer oriented nightclub and cabaret. Diet kept the tone of the club playful and yet avant garde, as the M.C. and booker. Because of Diet's generosity in allowing anyone to perform, Klubstitute became known as a breeding ground for new talent, as well as a space in which anyone of any sexual orientation could go to have some fun. In 1992, Diet founded Playstitute, a queer oriented theater production company. He died in 1995 of AIDS. Orloff, aka Remix, inherited Diet's unpublished scripts, lyrics, performance notes, and personal notebooks, which are included in the collection. Remaining active in San Francisco's cultural life, Remix has since published three novels, 'I Married an Earthling' (2000), 'Gutterboys' (2004), and 'Why Aren't You Smiling?' (2011) through Manic D Press.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Manuscripts, ephemera, photographs, posters, clippings, and other materials documenting the queer punk, performance and club scenes in San Francisco from the mid-1980s through the mid-1990s, at a time when AIDS was devastating the city's gay population and when the activist groups ACT UP and Queer Nation emerged in response to the epidemic. The papers focus on the Popstitutes and the many other initiatives by Collins and other group members and associates in the following decade, including Playstitute and Klubstitute. The personal collection of manuscripts, ephemera, posters, photographs and other materials documenting the groundbreaking queer punk, performance and club scenes in San Francisco from the mid-1980s through the mid-1990s, at a time when AIDS was devastating the city's gay population and when the activist groups ACT UP and Queer Nation emerged in response to the epidemic. With more than 425 leaves of typescripts and manuscripts and more than 900 items of ephemera and related materials, the collection offers rich primary sources for research in cultural studies, gender studies, queer studies, contemporary history, theater history, art history and related disciplines. The papers focus on The Popstitutes - a seminal San Francisco queer performance group and punk band founded in 1986 by Michael Collins ("Diet Popstitute," 1958-1995); Brad Kellogg ("Bad Popstitute"); and Alvin Orloff ("Remix von Popstitute")-and on the dizzying array of activities spawned by Collins and the other members and associates of the group in the decade that followed.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Orloff, Alvin, 1961-; Collins, Michael, 1958-1995.; Klubstitute (Nightclub); Playstitute (Theatrical production company); Popstitutes (Musical group)
Subjects:
Punk culture -- California -- San Francisco.; Gay culture -- California -- San Francisco.; Gay musicians -- California -- San Francisco.
Places:
San Francisco (Calif.) -- History -- 20th century.
Form and Genre Terms:
Ephemera.; Photographs.; Posters.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Dealer description and catalog. (Box 1, Folder 0)
- Alvin Orloff and Michael Collins Papers - Printed Guide, 1986-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Baby Judy's - Artwork, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Baby Judy's and Related Clubs - Print Materials, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Diet Popstitute (Michael Collins) - Manuscript Notebooks, 19-- (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Diet Popstitute (Michael Collins) - Obituary, Tributes, Memorial Events, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Diet Popstitute (Michael Collins) - Personal Papers, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Klubstitute: Ballstitute - The Clinton Inaugural, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Klubstitute - Handbills, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Klubstitute - Mailing List Sign-up Sheets, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Klubstitute - Miscellaneous Documents, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Klubstitute - Original Artwork - Paste-ups, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Klubstitute - Performer Documentation, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Klubstitute - Performance Texts, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Klubstitute - Posters and Flyers, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Klubstitute - Press Clippings, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Klubstitute - Press Releases, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Klubstitute - Promo Cards, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Klubstitute - Stickers and Sticker Masters, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Klubstitute - Unproduced Scripts, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Playstitutes - 'Carrie', 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Playstitutue - Flyers and Programs, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Playstitute - Miscellaneous Documents, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Playstitute - Phillip R. Ford's 'Dolls', 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Playstitute - Press Clippings, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Playstitute - Sondheimania One and Two, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Playstitute - 'Women in the Shadows', 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Playstitute - 'Wounded Children', 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Popstitutes - Flyers and Handbills - Artwork, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Popstitutes, Klubstitute, Playstitute, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Popstitutes - Miscellaneous Documents, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Popstitutes - Photographs, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Popstitutes - 'Play it Safe' Lyrics Book, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Popstitutes - Posters, Flyers, and Handbills - Print Versions, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Popstitues - Press Clippings, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Popstitutes - Programs - Artwork, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Popstitutes - Programs - Print Versions, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Popstitues - Song Lyrics, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Related Clubs, Events, and Groups - San Francisco, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Audio cassette tape with labels handwritten on masking tape, side 1: "Psycodrama The Heterosexuals / F*ck Irak" side 2: "My Wife Died" The cassette apparently includes recordings of spoken-word performances at Klubsitute. See "Performance Texts" folder., TR-9326 (Box 1)